Manuel E. Gondra Manuscript Collection:
Calendar of the Manuel E. Gondra Manuscript Collection, The University of Texas Library, prepared by Carlos Eduardo Castañeda, University of Texas, and Jack Autrey Dabbs, AM College of Texas. México: Editorial Jus, 1952.
- Eighteenth Century Documents (1778-1799)
  - 1597 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Orden del gobernador que el mayordomo de la catedral, Antonio Martínez Viana, haga un informe sobre las rentas de la misma.] Asunción, June 8, 1779. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 15. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155j])
  - 1598 Martínez Viana, Antonio. [Informe al gobernador sobre las rentas y gastos de la catedral de Asunción.] Asunción, June 9, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 15v-17. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155k])
  - 1599 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Orden al oficial real, Martín José de Aramburu, pidiendo informe sobre las asignaciones que tiene la iglesia catedral en la Real Caja.] Asunción, June 9, 1779. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 18. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155)
  - 1600 Aramburu, Martín José de. [Informe al gobernador sobre las asignaciones que tiene la iglesia catedral en la Real Caja.] Asunción, June 10, 1779. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 18v. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155m])
  - 1601 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta al dean y cabildo eclesiástico remitiendo documentos relativos a la necesidad de reedificar la iglesia catedral.] Asunción, June 17, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 19-21. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155n])
  - 1602 Vega, José Manuel de la. Relacion de la Literatura, Grados y Meritos Del Doctor Don Pedro Vicente Cañete y Dominguez, Asesor general del Virreynato de Buenos Ayres. Madrid, June 18, 1779. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3v-11. Modern copy from “Est. Aud. Charcas, Leg. 1, n[UNK] 6.” (Box [MG 1402b])
    Real universidad de S. Felipe de Chile; Pedro Tula Bazán, Agustín de Jáuregui, Pedro Ceballos, Juan de Casamayor, Juan Miguel de Aldunate, Juan José Domínguez y Yegros, Jacinta de Rojas y Aranda, Diego de Salas, and Juan José de Vértiz; interference in treatment of prisoners in Chile.
  - 1603 Bachicao, Manuel. [Certificación a S. M. de los repartos hechos de la gruesa de diezmos que han correspondido a la fábrica de la Santa Iglesia Catedral.] Asunción, June 24, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 22-23. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155o])
  - 1604 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO DE. [Acuerdo sobre las paces con los indios infieles de la nación lengua.] Asunción, July 12, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-17-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 157])
    Signed: Bernardino Robledo, Francisco Javier de Acevedo, Fernando Larios Galván, Antonio Caballero de Añasco, and José Cañete.
  - 1605 Melo de Portugal, Pedro de. [Carta a S. M. sobre la fundación de un colegio de misioneros franciscanos para la reducción de los indios infieles.] Asunción, July 13, 1779. 11 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-17-A, with two typewritten copies, each 7 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 176a])
    Military defense against Indians; suggestion for colonizing river bank opposite Chaco as means of defense.
  - 1606 Gallarreta, Pedro de. [Dictamen para la Contaduría General sobre la real cédula de 23 de agosto de 1776 aprobando creación de colegio seminario en Asunción.] Madrid, August 3, 1779. 10 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 23-32. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9-A. (Box [MG 1718g])
    Includes dictamen fiscal of the Consejo, Madrid, August 20, 1779, on funds for the college.
  - 1607 Vértiz, Juan José de. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre la reducción de Remolinos, fuertes de Curupaití y Humaitá, y la cuestión de límites entre Paraguay y Corrientes.] Buenos Aires, August 6, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-12-B, with a second modern copy from AGI 124-1-15, 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. (Box [MG 1088])
  - 1608 _____. [Carta a José Gálvez sobre la organización de las milicias de la Provincia del Paraguay.] Buenos Aires, August 6, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-12-A. (Box [MG 793])
  - 1609 ASUNCIÓN CABILDO ECLESIÁSTICO DE. [Carta a S. M. en que presentan razones en favor de la fundación de un colegio misionero franciscano en Asunción y dictamen fiscal de 22 de Febrero de 1780 aconsejando demora hasta que llegue un informe del Virrey.] Asunción, August 13, 1779. 10 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-17-A, with two typewritten copies, each 6 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 175])
  - 1610 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Orden al capitán José Coene que pase a la jurisdicción de misiones para hacer reconocimiento del azogue.] Asunción, August 23, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 15v-17. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-13-A. (Box [MG 797d])
  - 1611 Barbosa, José. [Orden en que manda se facilite a José Coene la inspección de las minas de azogue en la estancia de San Miguel paraje de San Lorenzo.] Santiago, September 8, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 22-24. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-13-A. (Box [MG 797f])
    Includes certificación by Manuel Aparicio, Pueblo de Nuestra Señora de Fe, September 16, 1779.
  - 1612 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO DE. [Carta a S. M. en que pide incorporación a la corona de todas las encomiendas de indios en la provincia del Paraguay.] Asunción, September 13, 1779. 15 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-15. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-20-A, with two typewritten copies, each 9 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 167a])
    Conditions of encomienda Indians. Signed: Bernardino Robledo, Francisco Javier de Acevedo, Fernando Larios Galván, Francisco Javier Benítez, Antonio Caballero de Añasco, José Cañete, Bernardo de Haedo, Fermín de Arredondo y Lobatón, and José del Casal y Sanabria.
  - 1613 Coene, José. [Auto en que dan relación del cumplimiento de la orden del gobernador sobre reconocimiento de las minas de azogue.] San Miguel, pueblo de Misiones, September 15, 1779. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 17-22. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-13-A. (Box [MG 797e])
    Assistance of Lieutenant-governor José Barbosa. Signed: José Coene, Antonio de Flecha, Manuel José Aparicio, Juan José Bogarín, and Juan Gabriel de Cárdenas.
  - 1614 _____. Razon del Auxilio que me dieron los Pueblos de Misiones, en cumplimiento de Carta de Oficio de mi Governador Dn. Pedro Melo de Portugal al The. Govor. dn. Joseph Barbosa. San Miguel, September 15, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 5-6. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-13-A. (Box [MG 797b])
  - 1615 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta al virrey, Juan José de Vértiz y Salcedo sobre las minas de azogue en el Paraguay y Misiones.] Asunción, September 21, 1779. 9 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 7-15. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-13-A. (Box [MG 797c])
    Inaccessibility of Paraguay mines; exploration of Chaco.
  - 1616 CONSEJO DE INDIAS? [Carta sobre reconocimiento de José Cañete y Antequera como hijo legítimo de José de Antequera y Castro y Micaela Sánchez de Vera y Aragón.] San Ildefonso, September 22, 1779. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-3-18-C. (Box [MG 871])
  - 1617 Vértiz, Juan José. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre Santa Fe como puerto de comercio.] Buenos Aires, October 8, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-12-C. (Box [MG 795])
  - 1618 Naude de la Bergeman, José. [Carta a S. M. sobre varias ocurrencias en los pueblos de indios en la provincia del Paraguay.] October 15, 1779. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 10-13. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-16-A. (Box [MG 1091d])
    Complaints against Agustín Pinedo and Manuel Fernández; their interference with commerce.
  - 1619 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Bando de buen gobierno.] Asunción, October 23, 1779. 3 p. 22 × 33 cm. p. 13-15. Modern copy from unnamed source. (Box [MG 93e])
    Order for 5 civil reforms; Santa Hermandad, Manuel Bachicao.
  - 1620 YUTÍ, CABILDO DE NUESTRA SEÑORA DEL. [Carta al visitador general pidiendo se manden religiosos doctrineros.] October 24, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 19-21. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153k])
    Written in Guaraní. Signed: José Antonio y Bandi, Santos Caruata, Juan Tupabera, José Ignacio Moviugo, Manuel Arazai, Roque Papayu, and Sebastián Ma Ude.
  - 1621 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Orden que todos los sujetos particulares que no tengan tierras propias y quieran adquirirlas en los términos de poblador se presenten a los jefes militares.] Asunción, November 3. 1779. 2 p. 22 × 33 cm. p. 1-2. Modern copy from V.37, no. 12? (Box [MG 2011a])
  - 1622 Naude de la Bergeman, José. [Carta a S. M. sobre lo acaecido en la provincia del Paraguay con perjuicio de la misma.] San Lorenzo, November 3, 1779. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 21-24. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-16. (Box [MG 1090g])
    Suit against Procurador Poncio for appropriation of property belonging to exiled Jesuits, brought by Juan Blas Perera and Juan de la Cruz Riberol; implication of Sebastián Montiel; abandonment of rich land by Agustín Pinedo between Río Tebicuarí and Río Tebicuaryminí; forced removal of José Casal, Asencio de Vera, José de Villanueva, Gabriel Benito; discovery of the Malvina Islands by Burqueville; petition by Naude for appointment as inspector of all Christian Indian villages of Paraguay.
  - 1623 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Orden que todos los sujetos que no tengan tierras propias y quieran adquirirlas se presenten a los jefes militares.] Asunción, November 3, 1779. 2 p. 22 × 33 cm. p. 11-12. Modern copy from unnamed source. (Box [MG 93d])
    Effort to colonize banks of Río Paraguay; Remolinos; La Herradura; Manuel Bachicao. See No. 1621.
  - 1624 Naude de la Bergeman, José. [Carta a S. M. aconsejando medidas para alivio de los abusos cometidos contra los indios.] San Lorenzo, November 3, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 18-20. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-16. (Box [MG 1090f])
  - 1625 SAN BLAS DEL ITÁ, CABILDO DE. [Carta al visitador Fray Gregorio Ascona dándole la bienvenida al pueblo.] November 6, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-2. Modern copy in Guaraní from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153a])
    Signed: Félix Uru, Juan Guaibití, Diego Faberé, Ivon Sapatero, Lucas Luna, Francisco Curuttey, Marselo Guarinipitá, Apolinar Uboiray, Mariano Yararepí, and Felis Yeraey.
  - 1626 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Resolución sobre la remisión anual de un reporte de los haberes del proyectado colegio en Asunción e informe de lo resuelto.] Madrid? November 8, 1779. 10 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 33-42. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9-A. (Box [MG 1718h])
  - 1627 Ascona, Gregorio. [Carta al gobernador comunicando gran necesidad de sacerdotes en los pueblos de Yutí y San Blas del Itá para impedir el retiro de los indios a la infidelidad.] Asunción, November 25, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 7-8. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153d])
  - 1628 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Auto sobre provisión de curas para los pueblos de Concepción de Yutí y San Blas del Itá.] Asunción, November 26, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 8-9. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153e])
    Penury of priesthood in Paraguay.
  - 1629 _____. [Decreto estableciendo los límites de la población de la Concepción de costa arriba.] Asunción, December 6, 1779. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 12v-15. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-25-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 151e])
  - 1630 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO DE. [Certificación a S. M. como son ciertos los puntos contenidos en la petición de Gregorio Ascona de esta fecha.] December 6, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 15-16. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153i])
    Signed: Bernardino Robledo, Francisco de Acevedo, Fernando Larios Galván, Antonio Caballero de Añasco, Francisco Javier Benítez, Bernardo de Haedo, Fermín de Arredondo y Lobatón, and José de Casal.
  - 1631 Ascona, Gregorio. [Carta al Cabildo de Asunción que certifiquen a S. M. sobre la fidelidad de los indios de Concepción de Yutí y San Blas del Itá.] Asunción, December 6, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 14-15. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153h])
  - 1632 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Certificación de las parroquias servidas interinamente por religiosos regulares a causa de la gran necesidad de sacerdotes clérigos en la provincia.] Asunción, December 7, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 9-10. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153f])
    Names of priests and parishes.
  - 1633 Carlos III. [Real cédula al gobernador del Paraguay aprobando la fundación de un colegio seminario en Asunción.] Madrid? December 13, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 43-45. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9-A. (Box [MG 1718i])
  - 1634 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre visita hecha para averiguar los cargos de José Naude contra el cura Manuel Fernández.] Asunción, December 13, 1779. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-4. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-16-A. (Box [MG 1091a])
  - 1635 Ascona, Gregorio. [Orden a Luis Pintos que traduzca al castellano la carta del cabildo de San Blas del Itá de 6 de noviembre de 1779.] Asunción, December 23, 1779. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153b])
  - 1636 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO ECLESIÁSTICO DE. [Certificación sobre la carencia de sacerdotes en el Paraguay.] December 24, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 11-13. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153g])
    Signed: Antonio Sánchez, Andrés Félix Quiñones, Pedro de Zamudio, and José Román Cabezales.
  - 1637 Pintos, Luis de. [Traducción de la carta del cabildo de San Blas del Itá a Gregorio Ascona.] Convento de San Francisco, December 29, 1779. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3v-6. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153c])
    Letter referred to is No. 1625 (MG 153a).
  - 1638 Martínez, Miguel Antonio. [Traducción de la carta del pueblo de Yutí al visitador general.] Convento del Paraguay [sic], December 30, 1779. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 22v-25. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153m])
    Letter referred to is No. 1620 (MG 153k).
  - 1639 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Dictamen que los de la religión de predicadores de Santo Tomás puedan conferir grados.] Madrid, 1779? 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 9-13. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 329b])
    Antecedents of the case; temporary license for granting degrees until university is established.
  - 1640 Naude de la Bergeman, José. [Carta a S. M. en que da cuenta de la opresión que sufren los indios del pueblo de Caazapá.] 1779? 10 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-10. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-16. (Box [MG 1090a])
    Prosperity of town under Fray Domingo de los Ríos; avarice and misrule of his successor, Fray Manuel Fernández; complicity of Agustín Fernando de Pinedo; economic ruin of town.
  - 1641 CONCEPCIÓN, POBLACIÓN DE. [Petición al gobernador que declare que todos los campos y montes al norte del Río Jejui pertenezcan a esta Población.] 1779? 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 11-12. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-25-A, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 151d])
    Signed: Sargento Mayor Félix de Escobar and twenty-seven other citizens.
  - 1642 Carlos III? [Real cédula al virrey del Río de la Plata en que pide informe sobre la reducción de los indios del Chaco.] 1779? 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-3. (Box [MG 1684])
    Report of José Román y Cabezales charging governor Pinedo with mistreatment of Indians; royal praise of cabildo and governor of Paraguay for establishing reductions.
  - 1643 _____. [Real cédula al virrey de La Plata en que reitera pedido de informe solicitado en anteriores cédulas en 18 de septiembre de 1778 y 27 de febrero del año corriente.] 1779? 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-3. (Box [MG 1683])
    Reductions in Gran Chaco.
  - 1644 Ascona, Gregorio. [Carta a S. M. sobre lo efectuado en su visita a la provincia del Paraguay.] Asunción, January 13, 1780. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 26-28. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-5-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 153n])
    San Blas del Itá and Concepción de Yutí in particular.
  - 1645 Naude de la Bergeman, José. [Carta a S. M. sobre los excesos intentados por Agustín de Pinedo y sus cómplices.] Madrid, January 24, 1780. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 5-8. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-16-A. (Box [MG 1091b])
    José Cabello and the Marqués de Osuna; conditions in Caazapá.
  - 1646 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Dictamen fiscal sobre la solicitud del cabildo eclesiástico de Asunción que se valide el testamento del difunto obispo.] Madrid, January 30, 1780. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 8-9. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155d])
    Prorogation of case pending Audiencia's decision.
  - 1647 Cáceres, Sebastián de. [Memorial al gobernador pidiendo se le conceda licencia para mantener sus animales en el potrero de enfrente del castillo de San Ildefonso.] Asunción, February 9, 1780. 4 p. 22 × 33 cm. p. 1-4. Modern copy from V-14-5-10. (Box [MG 526a])
  - 1648 Carlos III. [Cédula real a la Audiencia de Charcas ordenando que informen sobre la necesidad de reedificar la catedral de Asunción.] Madrid? February 11, 1780. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 24. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155p])
  - 1649 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO DE. [Dictamen sobre el memorial presentado por Sebastián de Cáceres.] February 14, 1780. 2 p. 22 × 33 cm. p. 4-5. Modern copy from V-14-5-10. (Box [MG 526b])
    Signed: José Antonio de Zavala y Delgadillo, Fernando Larios Galván, Francisco Javier Benítez, José Cañete, Bernardo de Haedo, and Sebastián Antonio de Villalba.
  - 1650 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Dictamen fiscal aconsejando demora sobre solicitud del Cabildo de Asunción sobre incorporación a la corona de los indios encomendados]. Madrid? March 13, 1780. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 15v-16. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-20-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 167b])
  - 1651 Arias, Francisco Gabino. [Carta al Virrey Juan José de Vértiz, en que comunica tener todo preparado para la expedición al Chaco y fundación de las nuevas reducciones.] Salta, April 25, 1780. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 620])
  - 1652 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO DE. [Carta a S. M. en que informa sobre los méritos del gobernador, Pedro Melo de Portugal.] April 28, 1780. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-8. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-22, with two typewritten copies, each 4 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. Also another modern copy, 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. from AGI 122-5-1-B. (Box [MG 439a])
    Guard at Macaipirá Pass, Nundiay, el Paraje de la Herradura, Pass of Tahibó, and Ñeembucú; settlements at Luruguy, Remolinos, and the Chaco; trouble with Indians in Chaco. Signed: Juan Tomás Yegros, Fernando Larios Galván, Antonio Caballero de Añasco, Bernardo de Haedo, Sebastián Antonio de Villalba, José Antonio de Zavala, Francisco Javier Benítez, José Cañete, Fermín de Arredondo y Lobatón, and Juan de Machaín.
  - 1653 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta al Virrey Juan José de Vértiz manifestando la fidelidad de la provincia.] Asunción, July 13, 1780. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3-4. Modern copy from AGI 122-4-21. (Box [MG 873b])
    False rumors in Buenos Aires of revolt in Paraguay.
  - 1654 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO ECLESIÁSTICO DE. [Carta al virrey comunicando el buen gobierno de Melo de Portugal y la fidelidad de la provincia a S. M.] July 13, 1780. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 4v-7. Modern copy from AGI 122-4-21. (Box [MG 873c])
    Increase in price of powder. Signed: Andrés Félix Quiñones, Antonio de la Peña, Pedro de Zamudio, and José Román y Cabezales.
  - 1655 Vértiz y Salcedo, Juan José de. [Carta del] virrey Vértiz al Rey sobre el establecimiento de nuevas reducciones de indios en el Chaco, en que le comunica que Don Francisco Gavino de Arias partió el 28 de Mayo para aquella frontera. Buenos Aires, July 18, 1780. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 619])
  - 1656 _____. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre explotación de minas de azogue en la provincia del Paraguay y envío de aquel producto a Potosí.] Buenos Aires, July 20, 1780. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-4. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-13-A. (Box [MG 797a])
    Proposal for a new colony on Paraguay River.
  - 1657 _____. [Carta al gobernador del Paraguay agradeciéndole el envío de carta declarando la lealtad de los vasallos de dicha provincia.] Buenos Aires, August 13, 1780. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-2. Modern copy from AGI 122-4-21. (Box [MG 873a])
  - 1658 _____. [Carta a S. M. en que da noticia del establecimiento de las reducciones de indios en el gran Chaco.] Buenos Aires, October 24, 1780. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1520])
    Incorporation of Mataguayos, Chumpís, Maivales, Signipés, Tobas, and Mocovís.
  - 1659 Mestre, Andrés. [Carta al virrey informando sobre visita a la intendencia del Tucumán.] Salta, December 25, 1780. 11 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-2-B. (Box [MG 827])
    Boundaries of Tucumán intendancy; plans to annex intendancy of Cuyo to that of Córdoba, and separate Tucumán and Jujuy.
  - 1660 Villasanti, Juan Ignacio. [Carta al Cabildo de Asunción solicitando remedio a los asaltos y robos de los indios del Gran Chaco.] 1780? 7 p. 22 × 33 cm. p. 28-34. Modern copy from ANA-v. 25 No. 14. (Box [MG 536])
    Indian suppressions effected by immediately preceeding governors.
  - 1661 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a S. M. en que informa sobre el estado de la provincia del Paraguay.] Asunción, 1780? 21 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-3. (Box [MG 1407])
    Communication with Potosí; southern boundaries of province; settlement of Spanish town of Ñeembucú as defense against savages; presidios along Paraguay River; boundaries with Brazil; Manuel de Flores; Bruno Mauricio de Zavala.
  - 1662 _____. [Decreto apoderando a José de Espínola que aprisione a los rebeldes de Montevideo.] Asunción? 1780? 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 7-9. Modern copy from AGI 122-6-18. (Box [MG 1840b])
    Revolt of a small band led by Isidoro Duarte Cabeza and including Bernardo Corvalán.
  - 1663 Arias Hidalgo, José Antonio. Descripcion Geografica y Subcinta de toda la Provincia del Gran Chaco Gualamba sus Qualidades extencion, y diversas Naciones conocidas, é Incognitas que le havitan sepultadas en las obscuras sombras de su Idolatria y Gentilidad. 1780? 30 l. 21 × 30 cm. Original unfinished manuscript. (Box [MG 82])
  - 1664 AMERICA MERIDIONAL PARTES INTERNAS. 1780? 10 l. 23 × 33.5 cm. Modern copy from Vol. 6, doc. 5, “Perú, Chile y Buenos Aires,” Dirección de Hidrografía, Madrid, 1901. (Box [MG 1940])
    Description of viceroyalty of Buenos Aires; its subdivisions; its Indians and vegetation; some historical data on mining.
  - 1665 DESCRIPCION [DEL VIRREINATO] DE BUENOS AYRES. 1780? 24 l. 23 × 33.5 cm. Modern copy from Vol. 5, 64a., doc. 11, of “Perú, Chile y Buenos Aires,” in the Dirección de Hidrografía, Madrid, 1901. (Box [MG 1944])
    Survey of history of the region since 1535 with emphasis on political divisions comprising the viceroyalty in 1777.